<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_input_observation_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2024 Google LLC

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

    https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_input_observation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="Creates an Input Observation Manager">
      This interface permits a surface to observe user input, even when the
      surface does not have the input device's focus.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroys the Input Observation Manager">
        Destroys the Input Observation Manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_observer">
      <description summary="Creates an observer for the surface.">
        Creates a position observation instance for pointer position relative to
        `surface`.

        The seat associated with the surface must have (or had)
        WL_SEAT_CAPABILITY_POINTER capabilitiey. Otherwise,
        WL_DISPLAY_ERROR_INVALID_METHOD is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_input_observer_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_input_observer_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="Input Observer">
      Permits observing input devices with respect to the associated surface.

      Status of input devices will be shared only when the surface is
      mapped. If the surface is destroyed, the server will destroy
      any associated observer, too.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroys the Input Observer.">
        Destructor.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="pointer_position">
      <description summary="Reports the pointer position.">
        Reports the pointer position relative to the surface.

        If the compositor displays the surface more than once, it may
        share the pointer position relative to each instance of the
        surface, identified by the `instance` argument. 

        The position is reported relative to the surface's edge vectors, and
        irrespective of whether the surface has input focus or whether the
        device's position is in- or outside of the surface area.

        The relative positions will be reported as signed 16:16 fixpoint
        values. Positions within the surface will also be reported, with
        values in the interval [0, 1) for both relative_x and relative_y.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="instance" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="relative_x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="relative_y" type="int"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

</protocol>
